# 哈喽 大家好
Hello, everybody.
# 最近去扬州呆了七八天现在回来
I went to Yangzhou for seven or eight days and now I'm back.
# 反正也快到了中秋节了嘛
It's almost Mid-Autumn Festival.
# 我跟我四伯爷买了点水果他上次说想吃石榴
I bought some fruit for my uncle. He said he wanted pomegranates last time.
# 这次我给他买点石榴 香蕉 还有这个火龙果
This time I got him some pomegranates, bananas and the dragon fruit.
# 他牙口不好
He has bad teeth.
# 然后我从那边带了盒月饼回来
I also brought a box of mooncakes.
# 现在过来看一下我四伯爷
Come and visit my uncle.
# 已经有一段时间没看到他了
I haven't seen him in a while.
# 我走扬州去了一趟
I went to Yangzhou.
# 我晓得 我看到你的视频了
I know. I saw your video.
# 这是那种噶
This is?
# 石榴
Pomegranates
# 石榴好吃
Pomegranates are delicious.
# 这个有籽噶
This one has seeds.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 坐撒坐撒 耍会儿
Sit down, sit down.
# 好好
Good
# 它要吃 你看
It wants to eat, you see.
# 你们是和这个籽一起吞下去的
Are the seeds edible?
# 籽不能吞 籽哪里吃的
You can't swallow the seeds.
# 他们都吃的
Some of them do.
# 我还是吃不来
I still can't swallow the seeds.
# 我就不吃
I won't.
# 籽不吃
not the seeds
# 你们吃这个石榴是不是连（籽一起吃）
Do you eat this pomegranate with the seeds?
# 只能吃这个水
I only drink the juice.
# 吃这个水噶我也觉得是
I think so.
# 籽不吃 籽吃不得
You can't eat the seeds.
# （猪肉）城里比我们农村还便宜一点这会
(pork) It's a little cheaper in the city than it is in our countryside.
# 是不
Really?
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 这会儿好多一斤嘛
What's the price now?
# 我们这卖二十六七
We sell it here for 26 or 27 per jin (500g).
# 二十六七
26 or 27
# 嗯 城里只卖得起二十五六
Well, in the city is about 25 or 26.
# 肉都嘛
Pork meat.
# 肉
Pork
# 四伯爷 喂一个猪来杀喂得到好久哦
Uncle, how long will it take to feed a pig?
# 那就看你喂得好还是差
That depends on whether you feed it well or poorly.
# 如果我是喂粮食喂得好安
If I was feeding it well (with corn and wheat).
# 喂粮食喂得好五六个月就要得
If you feed it with good food, it should take about five or six months.
# 五六个月啊
Five or six months.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 这个猪如果喂一年的话长得到好大哦 喂纯粮食
If you feed a pig for a year, how big will the pig become?
# 纯粮食喂起
Grain-Fed
# 就看猪的骨骼大小
It depends on the size of the pig's bones.
# 就一般的嘛
Just normal breed.
# 一般的还是三百七八
Usually about 370-380 jin (185-190kg).
# 三百七八啊
370-380 jin?
# 哦
Yes.
# 一个猪要长到三百七八啊
A pig can be that big?
# 三百 五六百斤都要长
Three hundred, even five, six hundred jins.
# 骨骼大小来安
It's depends on the size of bone.
# 那你选得来不
So you can choose the best piglet?
# 那肯定选得来撒
I'm sure I can make a good choice.
# 那你教我哈嘛
Teach me how to do it.
# 脚高点（长）的那种 然后脚要细点的
The ones with longer and thinner feet.
# 就不要那种大脚猪哈
Not those big foot pigs.
# 假如说这种猪养两个的话养得活不
If we had two of these pigs, could we feed them?
# 喂粮食容不容易生病安
Grain feeding will make pig healthier, right?
# 它就根据天气的气候了
It also depends on the weather.
# 像我们这种地方安
A place like ours.
# 我们这种地方热天还是要注意
You need to pay attention on hot days in a place like ours.
# 就跟你人是一个道理啊
It's just like human beings.
# 哦
Oh.
# 禁不起热
They can't stand the heat.
# 你给它把通风的风扇开起
You need to keep the ventilation fan on.
# 这个空气好 它凉快
When the air is good. It's cool.
# 它睡起就肯长
It grows when it sleeps.
# 还要加上一个和人一样要讲卫生
And also need to keep them as hygienic as human beings.
# 饲料猪和粮食猪 这个粮食猪可以卖到好多钱一斤安
Fodder pigs and grain pigs. The grain pig can sell for more money right?
# 那个饲料猪在市场销售价格上的话
What about the market price of fodder pigs?
# 可以说那个饲料猪便宜一块钱一斤
You can say that the fodder pigs are cheaper by 1 yuan per jin (500g).
# 便宜一块啊才
Only 1 yuan?
# 肉啊便宜一块钱一斤
Yes, meat is only 1 yuan cheaper.
# 粮食猪腌出来的腊肉也香噶
Grain pigs make good cured meat.
# 嗯 对对对
Yeah, yes.
# 我们这会喂一个的话可能
Is it possible to feed one now?
# 这会喂看你怎么喂
How can we feed it?
# 喂到过年
feed until the Chinese New Year.
# 看你买好大的
How big of a pig do you want to buy?
# 这会买的笼子猪（刚出笼的小猪）
The small piglets.
# 笼子猪肯定你喂不出来了
I'm sure you can't feed those small ones now.
# 喂不出来了
It's too late.
# 这会我们买粮食猪买得到不
Can we buy those grain feed pigs now?
# 那两天你不来 那两天我才买了四只猪
I just bought four pigs two days ago before you came.
# 是粮食猪啊
Grain pigs.
# 是粮食猪
It's grain pig.
# 你伯爷买的猪也是国家拿给他的
Your uncle bought pigs from the government.
# 国家给他的扶贫猪
Government gave him pro-poor pigs at fair prices.
# 扶贫猪
Poverty alleviation pigs
# 电子称称都有八两三 幺儿诶
Really good pigs.
# 你说那个猪人家喂得好不好
Those pig are so good.
# 肉好得很 我们弄起出去人家就买走了
The meat's so good, everybody wanted that pig as soon as we got it.
# 你四伯爷都没杀到
Your Uncle didn't even butcher them.
# 我只杀到一个半
I only got to butcher one and a half.
# 那越大的猪看得起
The bigger the pig, the better.
# 猪真的漂亮
The pig is really pretty.
# 明年喂 今年买
Next year I will feed one. I'll buy one this year.
# 今年这个猪还是买一个小点的 买个200多斤的
Probably buy another small pig this year... one that weighs about 200 jin (100kg).
# 200的好不好买哦
How about 200?
# 买个200斤的就可以了
Just buy a 200 jin one.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 这儿
Here
# 是好久嘛
It's still a long time to go.
# 腊月 腊月间
Twelfth lunar month
# 腊月初七
the seventh day of the twelfth lunar month
# 腊月初七是
It's the seventh day of the twelfth lunar month
# 冬至
Winter solstice
# 是好多号哦新历
What is the date of the solar calendar?
# 腊月初七
the seventh day of the twelfth lunar month
# 那上面看得到不
Can you see up there?
# 害怕是冬月哦 怎么是腊月哦
I think it's the eleventh lunar month. How can it be the twelfth lunar month?
# 冬月初七冬月初七
The seventh day of eleventh lunar month.
# 你好笨哦你
You're so stupid.
# 他一说起就是腊月 那里是冬月
He's talking about the twelfth. That's actually the eleventh.
# 冬月初七
the seventh day of the eleventh lunar month
# 就是十二月二十一号
That's December 21.
# 二十一号我们就自己买一个猪嘛 买一个粮食猪
On the 21st, we'll buy a pig, a grain pig.
# 又去买一个粮食猪是不
To buy a grain fed pig.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 现在这个农村来说
Now, in the countryside.
# 我看这个猪肉是便宜不下来的
I don't think this pork price is going to come cheaper.
# 应该是
You right.
# 没得错的
It has to be.
# 今天跟我四伯爷聊了很久
I had a long talk with my uncle today.
# 就是这个猪怎么喂
I know how to feed the pig now.
# 然后粮食猪跟饲料猪有什么区别
Also the difference between a grain fed pig and a fodder fed pig
# 今年我们想喂的话可能时间来不及了
We don't have time to do it this year.
# 还是下次
Next time.
# 下次有机会买一个农村的粮食猪撒
Next time I will feed a countryside grain pig.
# 弄一个猪来喂
Get a pig to feed.
# 明年开年来嘛
Next year after Chinese New Year.
# 开年来噶
At the start of the Chinese New Year.
# 开年来买嘛
Come and buy it.
# 要的要的
Yes, yes.
# 今年来不及了撒 今年还有好多点时间嘛
It's too late this year. There's no time left this year.
# 是 主要是今年也忙
Yeah, it's a busy year too.
# 大家都忙
Everybody's busy.
# 今年来不及了
It's too late this year.
# 好吧 本期视频到这里 拜拜
Okay, that's it for this video. Bye.
# 我们明年开始养猪 养来自己吃
We'll start raising pigs next year to eat for ourselves.
# 可以
Good